chapter 4.
I had thus learned a second fact of
great importance:
this was that the planet the little
prince came from was scarcely larger
than a house!
But that did not really surprise me much.
I knew very well that in addition to the
great planets-- such as Earth, Jupiter, Mars
and Venus which have been given names,
there are also hundreds of others which
are often so small that it is difficult
to see them through a telescope.
When an astronomer discovers one of
these he does not give it a name, but
only a number.
He might call it, for example, "Asteroid
325.
giving such a number to the newly
discovered planet or an asteroid makes
it very easy for the grown-ups to accept
the fact
I have serious reason to believe that
the planet from which the little prince
came is the asteroid known as B--612
the asteroid is so small that it cannot
be seen with a naked eye that is why it
has to be observed through a telescope.
That observation was by a Turkish
astronomer, in 1909..
On making his discovery, the astronomer
had presented it to the International
Astronomical Congress, in a great
demonstration.
But because of his Turkish costume
nobody had believed what he said.
Grown-ups are like that...
Fortunately, however, for the reputation
of Asteroid B--612, a Turkish dictator made
a law that his subjects, under pain of
death, should change to European costume.
So in 1920 the astronomer gave his
demonstration all over again, dressed in
style in an elegant suit
And this time everybody accepted his
report.
If I have told you these details about
asteroid b612 and made a note of its
number to you,
it is on account of the grown-ups and
their ways
grown-ups love figures When you tell
them that you have made a new friend,
they never ask you any questions about
essential matters. They never say to you,
"What does his voice sound like? What
games does he love best?
Does he collect butterflies?"
Instead, they demand:
"How old is he? How many brothers does he
have
How much does he weigh? How much money
does his father make?"
Only from these figures do they think
they have learned anything about him.
If you were to say to the grown-ups
I've seen a beautiful house made of
Rosie brick, with geraniums on the
windowsills and doves on the roof,"
they would not be able to get any idea
of such a house
You would have to say to them: "I saw a
house that cost four thousand pounds
Then they would exclaim: "Oh, what a pretty
house that is
thus if you say to them:
"The proof that the little prince existed
is that he was charming but he laughed,
and that he was looking for his sheep
now If anybody wants a sheep it proves
that he exists."
And what good would it do to tell them
that?
They would shrug their shoulders, and
treat you as if you were a child.
But if you said to them: "The planet he
came from was Asteroid B--612,"
then they would be convinced, and leave
you in peace from their questions.
They are like that.
One must not hold it against them.
Children should always show great
forbearance towards grown-up people.
But certainly, for those of us who
understand life
we could not care less about figures
I should have liked to start this story
like a fairy tale I should have liked to
say:
"Once upon a time there was a little
prince who lived on a planet scarcely
bigger than himself, and who had need of
a friend
To those who understand life,
that would have given a much greater
error of truth to my story.
For I do not want anyone to read my book
carelessly.
I have suffered too much grief in
setting down these memories.
Six years have already elapsed since my
friend went away from me,
with his sheep.
If I try to describe him here,
it is in order not to forget him.
To forget a friend
is sad.
Not everyone has had a friend.
And if I forget him,
I may become like the grown-ups
who are no longer interested in anything
but figures...
It is for that purpose, again
yet I have bought a box of paints and
some pencils.
It is hard to take up drawing again at
my age,
when I've never made any pictures other
than drawing a boa constrictor from the
outside and a boa constrictor from the
inside, since the age of six.
I shall certainly try to make my
portraits as true to life as possible.
But I'm not at all sure of success.
One drawing goes along all right
my mother has no resemblance at all to
its subject.
I make some errors, too
the height of the little Prince is not
right either
in one place he's too tall and in
another he's too short.
And I feel some doubts about the color
of his costume.
So I fumble along as best as I can,
now good how bad,
and I hope generally fair to middling
In certain more important details I
shall make mistakes, also.
But that is something that will not be
my fault and I must be forgiven for that
My friend never explained anything to me.
He thought, perhaps, that I was like
himself.
But I ALS do not know how to see sheep
through the wall of boxes.
Perhaps I'm a little like the grown-ups.
I have had to grow old